hello and welcome this is active
inference live stream
58.0 October 29th 2024 we're discussing
the paper from pixels to planning
scale-free active
inference so welcome to the active
inference Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on the slide this is a
recorded and archive live stream please
provide feedback so we can improve our
work all backgrounds and perspectives
are welcome and we'll follow video
etiquette for live
streams head over to active inference do
Institute to learn more about the
Institute get involved with projects
like live streams and a lot of other
things okay before we jump into the
paper let's say hello I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California and really
looking forward to this discussion Arun
want to say hi give any context and
thanks again for contributing to the dot
zero hi everyone my name is Aaron uh I'm
a software engineer in the UK uh I did
my PhD a good few years ago in which I
touched on Dynamic CS of modeling and
active inference uh I've been thinking
about it for a long time since then uh
and I came across uh this paper uh and
thought it was really hard and so I
requested guys can we do a live stream
on this I'd really love to understand
this paper properly uh and now I've
somehow ended up contributing to the
live stream uh so yeah all
good
okay so we're discussing this paper from
July 2024 from pixels to planning
scale-free active inference by Carl
friston and
colleagues the rest of this video is
going to be some background and context
and an introduction and an rview of the
ideas it's not a review it's not
comprehensive it will be part of an
exciting Series where in the coming
weeks in the one and two we discuss with
the authors and the two is going to fall
during the applied active Symposium so
that'll also be really fun okay let's go
to the big questions what are your big
questions or whether it's about the
paper specifically or what are the big
motivators that made you excited and
want to pursue these
affordances uh so I think the big one is
you know the title right and I think the
question of scale is one that's plagued
a lot of active inference uh
implementations and previous papers uh
in the past few years everyone's like oh
yeah I'd love an active inference agent
that can do stuff but if I have more
than a few States I get a combinatorial
explosion uh and things ever fall over
or they take a very long time uh
compared to uh alternative methods that
are out there um so the question of
scale is a really important one uh and I
think this paper nominally looks like
there's a way around that uh also the
renormalization group as a way to do
that is I think a very interesting one
uh it draws from a lot of physics uh
that I actually studied a very very long
time ago uh so that really uh spoke to
me and I thought it was really really
nice to see some things that apply to
also like icing model of pherom
magnetism uh some other uh key parts of
thermodynamics that now come into AI uh
which uh active inference has been doing
for a while with the free energy
minimization part uh but I think the
renormalization group is a really
interesting part of maths uh that seems
to get you a lot
further um I also had some like much
more technical questions which maybe
don't fall under the big questions which
will'll definitely come on to later when
I was reading this paper and going I'm
looking at it and I go I don't
understand actually what's happening
here so I'd really love to dive into
those and particularly catch up with the
authors in the later episodes to get
some of the more technical answers on
how these matrices Play and tensors play
together uh which seems to defer a
little bit to the textbook uh by par um
and some of the other formulations by
the RX and fur group as well uh so
actually getting into the nitty-gritty
of how we implement this will be really
fun for me cool
blue also contributed to the0 and so she
wrote what is a path more specifically
how are paths related to the
renormalization group how is the
renormalizing generative model rgm
different from the active inference
generative model that we usually study
and how do paths tie into transitions
between categories and I had similar
questions what is the renormalization
group how is it being used here how does
that make the generative models
structurally or functionally difference
how does that have implications for
different
media few key
claims they're considering one solution
to the implicit scaling
problem with scale free generative
models that are linked through the
renormalization group they're going to
explore generalized mdps Markov decision
processes as scret models that do
functional cognitive tasks like
compression content generation and
planning they're going to pay attention
to universality and scale and variance
for specifying structural form of
generative models and then there will be
a sequence of worked examples that we're
going to spend most of the zero walking
through and they highlight that these
kinds of rgms with quantized paths may
or may not be useful in certain
application domains so that's kind of
the meta ml question is where or how
would we know where this would or
wouldn't be more effective than another
given kind of model no free lunch at all
um could you read the
abstract uh yeah sure um so this paper
describes a discrete State space model
and accompanying methods for generative
modeling this model generalizes
partially observed markof decision
processes to include pars as latent
variables rendering suitable for active
inference and learning in a dynamic
setting specifically we considered deep
or hierarchical forms using the
renormalization group The ensuing
renormalizing generative models rgm can
be regarded as discrete homologues of
deep convolutional neuron networks or
continuous St space models in
generalized coordinates of motion by
construction these scale and variant
models can be used to learn
compositionality over space and time
Furnishing models of parves or orbits in
other words events of increasing
temporal depth and
itinerancy this technical note
illustrates automatic Discovery learning
and deployment of rgms using a series of
applications we start with image
classification and then consider the
compression and generation of movies and
music finally we apply the same
variation of principles to the learning
of Atari like video games
awesome okay moving on to Daniel you're
on
mute thanks to the road
map the first section is the
introduction section two is the
background formalism this is going to
make connections with the generative
models from the textbook then section
345 6 we'll go through a sequence of
worked examples we're going to frontload
the focus in the zero on sections two
and three and then four five and six
unfold kind of naturally three is a
static image mnist handwriting data set
task section four is a cyclic video that
then slides in into a chaotic attractor
dynamical system section five and a
natural video section five goes into
sound and six is the general planning
case from pixels to planning and Seven's
a short conclusion so it's pretty much
introduction and conclusion like book
ends section two is where the general
formalism is and then 3 through six take
us on from
handwriting several kinds of videos
Dynamic images sound and then gameplay
and
planning here are the keywords of the
paper active inference Active Learning
basian model selection renormalization
group compression structure learning RG
flow renormalizing generative model so
those are good terms if you're uncertain
about to jump into okay we have a few
slides on some of these background
Concepts just to get it upfront so we
can proceed
with the paper when we get there let's
start with what is renormalization so of
course much could be said but Anin what
what would you say what is
renormalization yeah so I think this is
in itself uh quite a loaded term there's
a lot from physics uh and if you look at
the Wikipedia page the third link uh
that's there uh there's a lot uh in that
Wikipedia page it's very confusing a lot
of quantum electrodynamics coming in and
I think Fineman has an attitude on it he
says he's not a fan of it um but uh I
think for our purposes the top quote
that's there that's come from the paper
is actually good enough for a large part
so we basically take some sort of system
and we say this is way too hard this is
way too complex there's way too many
moving
Parts what is a like a take-home message
what is the summary of what this is
doing at a macroscopic level compared to
the micro level
uh and there are some examples in uh the
upcoming slides on particularly talking
about thermodynamics and materials where
this will become more obvious as to how
this might work in practice uh but I
think the coar grained version that
retains the properties of interest is
really what to focus on uh going forward
and yeah lossy compression for the um
signal processing engineers in the
audience uh this is very much a case of
you're not keeping everything when you
read normalize you're keeping what's
important awesome yeah as you coar grain
so spatially like thinking about a
radius or like a convolutional diameter
getting larger and larger you're
choosing a bigger chunk to grain over
coar graining and renormalizing what
those edges and relations amongst blocks
are so you have one model it's a 10x 10
square so you have block exercise one
and all those edges and then you decide
okay we're going to look at blocks of 2
by two you have fewer blocks fewer edges
so you have to renormalize all of your
parameter estimates and then you end up
with hopefully capturing some of the
signal with fewer parameters AKA
compression whether it's lossy or
lossless okay and you I'm going to pick
up on one thing quickly where you said
spatially and you can renormalize
through space but you can also
renormalize through time you can
renormalize through any Dimension you
want uh it's just easier to imagine the
space and time ones so the time analogy
that I think they use in the paper which
is quite a good one is thinking about if
you're uh let's say you're watching TV
and you're watching something and in
that moment there is there are two
characters talking that might form part
of a scene which is one
renormalization and then you have a
series of scenes which would be an
episode and then you'd have multiple
episodes in a series right so the time
one actually I find a bit more intuitive
to understand what renormalization is
and you can say oh yeah something
happened in a particular episode you can
say something happens in a particular
series something happens in a particular
scene but that thing you might be
describing might actually be more fine
grained or more Co grained awesome yeah
the examples will start with the static
handwriting and move on to include time
and you're totally right about the time
scales it's like saying what's the
transition Matrix from minute to minute
or hour to hour or day to day but moment
is measurable with seconds minutes hours
or so on okay how about the spin block
transformation uh yeah so now this is
sort of back to um Material Science and
magnetism uh so there's a fairly well
understood model of magnetism uh called
the ising model um physicists generally
quite like it mathematicians quite like
it um as you you imagine a big magnet as
lots of little magnets uh that are all
line up in a grid uh and each magnet
just talks to the little magnets around
it uh and you can recover quite a lot of
sort of actual behavior of magnets uh in
the real world with a fairly simple
model for this um but the spin block
transformation is largely going well if
I have uh lots of little magnets
together and they're all pointing the
same way I can just think of it as one
big magnet that's some that's the sum
behavior of all of these little ones uh
and this is a trick that we play a lot
in physics of going from the micro to
the macro the micro is too hard to model
it's too painful you got all these
particles they could all be doing you
know spinning Every Which Way all their
speeds and velocities and if you had all
of them then you could add them all up
and you could figure out what's going on
or you can just you know get a
therometer and measure the temperature
right and the temperature that one
number tells you a lot about how this
thing is going to behave so you can get
a lot of value just from the macro but
that macro is composed of all of the
micro so depending on where you are in
your course graining of your scaling
Behavior Uh you can get either a lot
done or a little bit done and it's just
what's useful to you uh so I quite like
uh this uh sort of quot at the bottom um
about the magnitude of an observable of
a physical system undergoing an RG
transformation and whether that
observable is relevant or not I think
that's quite important to bear in mind
for the future examples of well if
something is always increasing it's
always getting bigger then you're going
to see it on the coar grained
Transformations that you see later but
if it's always decreasing at a
particular level you're not going to see
it on the higher levels you're only
going to see it on the lower levels so
it'll have so they this gives you some
uh understanding of causality of whether
when you're going up or when you're
going down uh on the course raining um
so yeah like particle speeds and
temperature is a nice uh a nice uh
example of this and similarly magnetism
with the spin block transformation um
but by and large what are these
transforms doing if you take a grid of
lots of little things you just go well
I'm just going to summarize this with a
single thing that represents that
behavior and then move on with my
day awesome okay quick on the singular
value
decomposition there's a nice interactive
explanation this is related to principal
component analysis
and it's a way to proportion variance
and to take the biggest cut of variance
for a given decomposition for a data set
and you can take we'll look at it in
application a bit later but it's used to
to assess the vectors of variance and
then you can truncate them and use that
to to capture increasing amount of
variants for a given data set we'll look
at it in a specific case and last kind
of background topic on locality
principle uh yeah I don't actually know
a huge amount the about the locality
principle um but I think it's a general
intuition that things next to each other
affect each other and things far away in
theory don't affect you uh there are
definitely some things where if this is
violated this feels very weird uh I
think quantum inang is probably an
example of that uh but I'm going to stop
speaking there because we've hit the
limit of my knowledge yes I think Vicken
Stein wrote something about that okay
and this is just a few of the other
links but there was a ton of other links
that people brought up over the months
preparing for this okay onto the paper
so here's the link to the Koda I'll put
this in the YouTube live chat right now
just if anyone wants to follow back to
the workspace where we did the
preparation work if you're watching live
write any questions in the live chat and
we'll check it at the end what we're
about to do is go through much of the
paper pulling out some of the key quotes
and the main thread and we show most or
all the figures and some of the
formalisms of course they're all there
in the paper this is just the highlights
so that we can get this done in a
reasonable linear amount of time in
preparation for conversations with
authors further open source development
and all that so okay here we go onto the
paper
so first three sentences of the paper
this paper considers the use of discret
State space discret State space models
as generative models for classification
compression generation prediction and
planning so for context we're in the
discrete time
setting figure 4.3 from the 2022
textbook we're in the top
setting the inversion of such models can
be read as inferring the latent causes
of observable outcomes or content so
this is the tale of two densities
meaning that generative models can be
used to generate synthetic observations
from lat and state estimates that's the
generative direction or decompression as
well as in fer latent States from data
that's the recognition direction from
observations to latent States and then
last of these three sentences when
endowed with the consequences of action
they can be used for planning as
inference so in contrast with sort of a
sterile sensemaking or perceptual
inference task active inference
considers action as part of a joint
inference distribution or problem which
constitutes the agent so think about how
the agent is defined as AB CDE matrices
as sensemaking lat and state transition
operations and the consequences of
action so improvements to generative
modeling technologies have wide ranging
implications for a variety of both
sensemaking perception tasks on the
inbound as well as decision- making and
action tasks on the outbound which is
kind of the theme of active inference
that action can be treated as an
inference problem any thoughts on these
first lines
um no I think we keep going cool okay
specifically this paper explores the use
of generalized marov decision processes
this generalization in question rests on
equipping a standard partially observed
marov decision process PDP with random
variables called
paths this affords an expressive model
of Dynamics in which transitions among
states are conditioned upon paths which
themselves can have law full transitions
so we're going to return to this figure
again but the big picture is that from
the sort of textbook basic PDP we're
going to add some
sophistication which is that variables
called paths will condition the state
Transitions and those could fall under
the agency or the efficacy of an agent
or not there can be lawful probabilistic
transitions among paths which are like
transitions amongst actions in a policy
sequence except that actions in a policy
sequence would be understood to be under
the control of an agent and and those
paths States influence transitions of
Laten States figure one shows that
several concepts of depth in generative
model we have temporal depth which means
a deeper unrolling through time so this
is just predict predicting more time
steps deeper into the future linearly so
if this was each one was one day this is
just going rolling out for bigger number
of days hierarchical depth would be if
we had a model that had days months and
years and the way that it could deal
with longer time scales would be have 30
days within a month and then 12 months
within a year and so nested
hierarchically recursive layers deal
with deeper time scales instead of
needing to unroll 365 days and factorial
depth can be thought of kind of like a
multi- sensory model so here's an
observation of sound and here's an
observation of light and then those
different modalities can be factorized
separately from each other like the what
and the where and the Brain to simplify
and that's another way in which
generative models can have
depth any more thoughts on this
uh I think one thing to highlight is uh
first of all the notation is quite
difficult to understand in this figure
um I found it really hard uh there is
also a dis I think there is a difference
at least in my mind when I read this
figure in the caption compared to say
the textbook which is the C Matrix um so
I think previous formulations of actor
inference uh the C Matrix tends to
represent uh the prior preferences of an
agent uh sort of its goals its values
it's like I expect to see these
observations so if I don't then I I'm
going to experience a higher free energy
so I'm either going to change my mind or
change take some action to change the
world so that my observations match my
prior better and I get a lot of free
energy here the C Matrix seems to be
encoding probabilities of
paths it's not entirely clear to me how
we get value into that as opposed to
just what it expects to see so maybe
there is a distinction here that I
haven't understood or maybe maybe it is
genuinely a shift um I'd be really
curious to ask the authors specifically
about the C Matrix and how that behaves
uh in the future episodes yeah pending
authors accounts but two things I would
note to Echo that first is every
variable Through Time can be understood
as a trace or a path whereas path is
also being used to refer to just this
specific upstairs string and then a
second case of overloading is C while in
previous situations like in figure 7.3
or 4.3 from the textbook we have C as
playing a role in expected free energy
calculation pragmatic value the
preference over observations here it's
not the same c c as preferences is over
observations here
transition probabilities are encoded in
C so it's kind of like a b but this just
goes to show letters are just letters
and future software will be able to flip
out and have different shapes and
notation and all of that so don't get to
attach to the letter look at how they're
locally defining things even though that
can be really challenging learning too
okay the generalization becomes
particularly important when composing
maravian processes in deeper
hierarchical
architectures this follows from the use
of States at one level to generate the
initial conditions and paths at a lower
level this recursive aspect speaks to a
definitive feature of the generative
models considered in this paper
renormalizability this is the big idea
multiscale hierarchical models can be
built using this paths on States on
paths on States on paths an dot dot dot
dot dot do dot method which describes
this rorm ization happening across
scales so you could have the inch by
inch path and then that's nested within
a foot by foot and mile by mile or you
could have the minute by- minute path
and that's nested with an hour by hour
and day by day so by having this
layering of states and paths and states
and paths there's a clean way to get the
separation of spatial or temporal or
arbitrary
scales
so that's the big background formalism
one other way to get an intuition here's
from our paper on the renormalization
group in free energy principle app
applied to multikill biological systems
on the bottom we have the kind of figure
that we've seen in many active inference
papers where we're thinking about like
the cognitive behavioral entity like a
worm where the sensory States can be
associated with perception active states
with action internal states with
cognitive States and all of
that at the end of the day there's also
this nested extended evolutionary
process that is happening at the
population scale so that's kind of like
nesting the phenotype of individual
worms within a population of worms or
within an ecological
distribution um and then last note here
in this setting a policy is not a
sequence of actions but a combination of
paths where each hidden Factor has an
Associated State and path this means
there's potentially as many policies as
there are combinations of
paths so because these paths are kind of
like
context
combinations it means that there's a
double explosiveness to
them so understanding how do you handle
that and understand the computational
complexity class and again where it
wouldn't wouldn't be useful those are
key
questions any
thoughts yeah I think that that last bit
especially in a paper that's called
talking about scale reactive inference
and then now we're not just combining
States for that explo that combinatorial
explosion now it's combinations of Paths
of states and
actions uh in theory this should be much
worse
so I think at the moment I'm reading
this and I'm thinking we're going to pay
even more of a cost in terms of
computing what the hell is going on uh
but I think the renormalization group
and making these models
hierarchical pays for it that's that's
my that's my intuition of reading this
paper so uh yeah it's a there a good
quote to have there and it's a good
thing to have bouldered it's uh you I
don't think you're ever going to get a
free lunch but you have to pay for lunch
yeah the number of ingredients for lunch
um
okay in what follows we illustrate
applications of the renormalizing
generative model rgm in several
settings um the renormalization group
requires the functional form of the
Dynamics terms of belief updating is
conserved over levels or scales this is
assured in variational inference in the
sense the inference process itself can
be cast as pursuing a path of least
action where action is a path integral
of variational free energy another
classic term overloading action here
isn't like the robot moving its arm this
is the physics action sometimes with a
capital A because all inference under
free energy principle is considered in
terms of a path of least action we can
be assured that arbitrarily thick wide
thin tall small world however you want
to create the topology of generative
model we can be ensured that we're in an
analytical setting where the models are
quote doing the same thing at different
scales and then this takes us all the
way from the first principles framing of
the problems all the way on through the
software tools like RX and fur which
might be implementing these kinds of
generative models also in this kind of
ecumenical way the only thing that
changes between levels are the
parameters of the requisite action EG
sufficient statistics of various
probability
distributions that's to say the
functional properties of the rgm are
simply determined and described by how
it's parameterized so was it statistics
all
along and that's what we have in figure
three with um showing what that blocking
looks like these are statistical
parameters that are learned so the
description of the topology of this
graph is the structure which is either
fixed or designed or set or learned as a
structure learning problem and then
there's the values for a given situation
that these variables take on and here's
that state path essential coupling
that's the state Path State path so
compare this with hierarchical or
multi-level basian regression compare
this with hierarchical predictive
processing architectures State Path
State path and each of those constitute
a separation of scales all of this is a
statistical
model any thoughts on
this yeah I think there's the hierarchy
part is absolutely key here um there is
a little aside in the paper about which
things in a hierarchy can affect which
things in the lower part uh to make the
inference actually possible so this is
the idea of the markof blankets and uh
whether you whether a child can have
like multiple parents that sort of thing
um I think we possibly will come on to
that later um but overall the main
critical thing is stuff happening at a
higher level in your hierarchy is
determining a lot of what's happening at
the lower level but information can flow
back up with the observations that you
get at the lower level to infer those
parameters at the higher level so that's
the classic Act of inference sort of top
down bottom up approach
yeah awesome okay next section active
inference learning and selection this
section overviews the model which is
used in the numerical studies of the
following section and figure one
provides an overview of the generative
model that's considered in the paper we
already took a quick look outcomes at
any time depend upon hidden States
that's the a matrix that's the partially
observable part while transitions among
hidden St stes depend on paths and
that's this sort
of uh way that we see the transitions
amongst latent States so that's the B
Matrix which is intervening between
hidden States s b is being imposed upon
by this path happening so it's almost
like this is a uh this is like a a a
rail or a guide up top that's
influencing how the actual latent State
ends up unfolding through time and at
each time Point there's the emission of
an observation that's the generative
direction or it could be taking in an
empirical data point and then updating
beliefs through time
um they describe the variables just like
in the
caption the tensors are generally
parameterized as dlay distributions
whose sufficient statistics are
concentration parameters or deay counts
which count the number of times a
particular combination of states and
outcomes has been inferred we focus on
learning the likelihood model encoded by
dearly counts a and that's known as
learning by counting so that's the kind
of classic case of pulling balls out of
an n and then tallying every time you
see a certain kind of ball coming out of
an urn or here it would be like pulling
balls out of an n and it's either cloudy
or sunny
and then you're doing learning by
counting on the context and the outcome
and then you're using that to
parameterize everything
else carrying on a little bit with this
and again connecting back to the
textbook compare with figure 7.3
PDP the details are basically the same
except notice that paths U are described
as we mentioned ear
C in the textbook just the letter c it's
not actually that variable
computationally but the letter c is
being used for preference distributions
over observations here C is playing a
role in the transition it's kind of like
a b but for this meta
path in the textbook we have a single
layer model now it has compositionality
but it's just a single layer model
whereas in the paper we're discussing
today hierarchical levels are described
in terms of this state Path State path
alternation approach and there's
factorial
depth here the procedural order of
operations for the generative model is
provided as policy
selection generate hidden State
sequences and generate expected outcomes
this is the forward or generative
direction we could also go the
recognition direction from real
observations to policy inference so
they're
unrolling a policy Centric approach that
yields expected outcomes that's like
running the generative model from policy
inference
out as opposed to running a generative
model from data processing to belief
updating about policy going
in just to highlight some kind of points
of contact similarities with the
textbook for those H Apple any
comments uh no I think that was really
good awesome p okay uh equations 1 2 and
three in this paper are akin to equation
2.5 and 2.6 in the textbook on
variational free energy and expected
free energy so to learn about the
different decompositions of variational
free energy in terms of the ones that
look more statistical like Divergence
minus evidence complexity minus accuracy
or the ones that look more statistical
physical like energy and entropy that's
variational free energy and then
analogously with equations two and three
in the paper or equation 2.6 in the
textbook we have expected free energy
with the classical decomposition into
epistemic value pragmatic
value okay now we get to active
inference um there's a lot we could say
here they describe that first sentence
of active inference section in
variational inference and learning
sufficient statistics encoding posterior
expectations which could be about sense
making as well as action posterior
expectations about what I am going to do
PI are updated to minimize variational
free energy so that's the idea of seeing
everything it is that the agent isn't
does on the inbound perceptual and
outbound action selection as part of a
joint distribution that's undergoing
variational free energy
minimization that's the active inference
concept note the circle with a DOT
notation so the notation implies a sum
product operator the dot or inner
product that sums over one dimension of
a numeric array or tensor so note the
difference
between circle with a DOT as the inner
product or tensor contraction while
circle with X is the outer
product so to look at the figure with
message passing and which brings in this
circle with a DOT
notation here we see the same graph that
we saw in figure one in figure one we
have a base graph so the nodes are
variables that we would encode in our
program and then the edges are caus a
relationship so that's the kind of
classic systems modeling kind of flow
interaction mind map here in this figure
we
see a factor graph representation now in
live stream 55 and in the realizing
synthetic active inference agents
discussion other discussions we've
talked more about the relationship
between Bas graph and the forny factor
graph representation suffice to say that
what it is that nodes and edges are
basically get flipped but there's a full
reproducibility so that here we have
ways to look at the logistics of message
passing amongst these nodes and it turns
out that under the hood this is what RX
and fur is doing when it's being
implemented so maybe if we get more into
implementation we could talk about that
this figure is just showing that for
that PDP
which is going to be doing the real work
of active inference on the perceptual
and the action selection side it's not
just that we can link up the variables
on the base graph that account for what
we want to do it's that there's a
specific Logistics and we know exactly
which messages to pack and send in order
to get this whole variational inference
done at the graph level and that can be
done with either a determined logistical
schedule or it can be done in a reactive
message passing
setting okay Active Learning basing
model reductions a generalization of
ubiquitous procedures and
statistics in the present setting it
reduces to something remarkably simple
by applying base rules to parent and
reduced models so a model of K
parameters and of K minus one parameters
it is straightforward to show that the
change in variational free energy can be
expressed in terms of posterior derish
lay counts a prior counts a and the
prior counts that Define A reduced
model so a
prime corresponds to the posterior one
would have obtained under the reduced
priors the alternative to basy model
reduction is bottomup growth of models
to accommodate new data or content if
one considers the selection of one
parent model over another augmented
model as an
action these two equations in the act of
learning section are like the add and
remove variable operations and
ultimately what allow us to compare any
basian model so model comparison amongst
nested strictly nested models can be
done in the fully parametric setting
using the hierarchical likelihood ratio
test basian models allow model
comparison amongst models that differ in
only one parameter like adding or
removing one parameter as part of
structure inference or there can be
radically different model topologies
underneath and that can be evaluated in
terms of like a base Factor support for
one model over
another it also connects to a lot of
work theoretical and applied in sleep
wake type models where parameters are
added fit increases during wake cycles
and then synapses are pruned models are
reduced core graining occurs during
sleep and the big picture is you can use
basian model comparison framed as a free
energy landscape optimization just as
always comparing different base graphs
comparing different generative models
and then this results in the expression
of a log base factor or an odds ratio
comparing the likelihood of two
different models so this allows
comparison of different models and the
selection of different models as its own
inference
task any thoughts on
this yeah just one thing I want to pick
up on is uh I actually can't remember
like I guess with this paper I think
they were just doing sort of like the
it's almost like just purely the bottom
up approach right uh they're not
starting with like a massive model and
then you couldn't like start with a very
big one at the top and then C grain down
you have to C grain sort of going up the
hierarchy as it were so I think we end
up going with this bottom up growth of
models because you don't want more
levels than you need necessarily or like
if you have your if you have an image
and you're trying to classify it and
it's I don't know 32x 32 pixels and you
just subdivide it by two you need to
start with your pixel you need to start
with your full image width first and
then course grain course grain course
grain up rather than going ah a priorite
I'm going to have n levels and then cut
them down after so I think that's we're
probably going to be more on the um
bottom up growth of models for this
particular paper yeah good point how do
you know how big to make each scale and
how many
scales
um won't read all the text on this page
but big claim renormalizability is
feasible under the models in figure one
so that's kind of the rhetorical chain
is here's the models that we're working
with in figure one these models have
renormalization properties that is what
makes this state Path State path
layering amenable to scale-free or scale
friendly or multiscale generative models
the claim is that given the
renormalization properties of Bas graphs
like or including the ones that they're
describing with this state Path State
path nesting there can be
computationally tractable possibly
multi-level renormalization and the rest
of the paper they're going to be
explaining and unpacking that and
adapting it to specific
settings uh these renormalizing
Transformations have the effect such
that the Dynamics slow down in time and
space as one ascends levels or scales so
compare that with other work on
information theory of individuality or
bottom up and top down information flows
and causality gapping and
lading and also they're saying that the
structure and the tuning of the
variables in the graph which would yield
the full reproducible description of the
renormalizable generative
model itself can be reached through this
basian model
comparison we had some questions about
how the discret and continuous time are
different a more intuitive view is that
successively higher levels encode
sequences of sequences and implicitly
composition of events or episodes in
other words at a deep level one state
can generate sequences of sequences of
sequences thereby destroying the
maravian properties of content generated
at the lowest level so this is like
encoding or sedimenting
nested sequences or paths in event based
or order structured
narratives deep structure is what allows
for possibly Advanced or naturalistic
interpretable fill in your preferable
adjective there models of complex
phenomena that do have deep structure
like speech and writing and
story and they're going to be walking
through renormalization through space in
terms of pixels time and in general
spaces so it's cool to think about like
Chris fields and Mike Levens work on
competency in navigating arbitrary
spaces as an invariant for analyzing
cognition in diverse embodiments so the
idea that space and time are just some
State spaces but other state spaces like
semantic embeddings from an llm or other
kinds of State spaces might also have
these abilities to to yield to the
renormalization
operation any
comments uh no those all good
cool figure three is a graphical model
which we we looked at a little earlier
where groups of States at a lower level
are generated by a single state at a
higher level so here we have a state at
a higher level s sub1 superscript n
plus2 and then flowing out of it we have
the state and the path at a lower
level higher states only change after a
fixed number of Lower State change so
that could be two it could just be twice
as fast like a frequency doubling every
time there's a time scale separation or
it could be fixed like 60 minutes per
hour or Andor it could be fully reactive
in terms of using RX and fur for uh just
in time type responsive updating and
this is somewhere where I think that
generalized notation notation will be
really helpful because talking about
what these variables are in detail gets
pretty
messy um because each state and path has
only one parent the insuring markall
blanket the blue Circles of each state
red circle ensures conditional
Independence among latent factors there
is a strict uni parental inheritance
factorization pattern in the
hierarchical model so latent factors
remain conditionally
independent so note that the S and the U
here are not
connected conditioned upon the higher s
they are conditionally
independent that simplifies the runtime
inference In Sum a renormalizing
generative model
rgm is a hypergraph parameterized by two
sorts of tensors the A and the b in
which the children of States at any
level by partition into initial States
and paths in this Example The Blocking
transformation groups pairs of states
and
paths so here it's kind of like a and b
again not exactly the A and the B
letters from the textbook but note that
a describes the likelihoods or empirical
priors and B is the Dynamics so a is
broadly referring to like this
instantaneous sense making like
relationship between latent States and
observations whereas B is describing the
Dynamics and the transitions through
time so I'm not sure if it's exactly
that simple but a is kind of describing
synchronous attributes of the model
whereas B describes diaconis Through
Time aspects of the
model OKAY anything
else yes I think one thing to really
hook on to is the uniparental
inheritance thing so I think you're
correct in when you say yes that makes
everything faster and less
computationally uh difficult that is a
good thing uh but I think there's a more
philosophical thing to raise as well
which is when we're talking about
causality going up and down the levels
uh and learning should in theory be a
lot easier uh when you only have a
single cause for something so that means
that when you make an observation it's
much easier to infer oh the parent must
have been this in order to cause what I
see and you don't have to consider
multiple factors coming in and going ah
well it could have been any one of 10
different factors that mean I saw what I
saw so that learning process as well
when we talking about the dlay counts
earlier should be a lot easier to do
when you have only a single parent uh
for a particular uh variable
um so yeah that conditional Independence
among latent factors I think also
features into the locality aspect as
well of uh when we were talking about
the very beginning of the session but
I'm not 100% sure on that but that's my
intuitive understanding of what's going
on that cool
okay one can also regard rgm as an
expressive way of modeling
non-linearities in the limit of precise
likelihood mappings this can be viewed
as the compositional of logical
operators one can see why an rgm can
compose operators to represent or
generate content that has compositional
structure the inversion of an rgm could
be construed as a simple form of
abductive EG modal logic okay now we're
going to get to the
examples here we go first example image
compression and
compositionality so first it's helpful
for background to look at variational
Auto encoders these take in some input
observations they project down to a
latent Stace SP Stace that's smaller and
then decode out to
reconstruct so it's really similar to a
variational auto encoder and look at the
first word variational free energy
variational Auto encoder they just call
it the Elbo not the vfe there's so many
similarities between this method and
active inference that it's really
helpful to study up it just sometimes
uses a little bit of a frame shifted
ontology here's what they
do they're studying the classic mnist
handwriting data set they map continuous
pixel values to a discrete State space
and then they're going to learn the
structure through recursive applications
of a blocking
transformation they group together local
pixels by tiling or tesselating the
image so that's the first step is they
tesselate over the image at multiple
scales so the smallest dots is a 4x4
cluster of pixels then the mediumsized
dot is four of those so then 1 2 3 four
these get clustered into this one and
then 1 2 3 4 get clustered into that one
and so on so that's the spatial static
renormalization via spin block locality
principle process
each group is then subject to singular
value
decomposition given the training set of
images to identify orthagonal spatial
bases of singular vectors so this is the
grouping and the reduction grouping is
the tessellation it's like a convolution
we'll talk more about how it differs
from convolution like a convolutional
neural n and then they truncate so
here's an example from the form index
project but there's many other places
you could look at this this is what for
a principal component analysis or for an
SVD
analysis every single time it selects
the vector that explains the most
orthagonal variance and then it takes
that profile out of the original data
and then it takes the next most variance
explaning vector and so you end up with
something that looks like a variance
explanation curve so the first 10
components explain 70% to get to 90% on
this data set it took 50 so if you say
well my computer only has space for 10
just take 10 or if you say well I'm
interested in this kind of Bas optimal
parto optimal crossover point you can
solve it that way um or maybe you have
other constraints so that's pretty much
how it's working is they're structurally
using the nesting with these 4x4 spin
glass
blockings and then
they do a SVD truncation compression
method on each level of that
blocking this is how the Path State Path
State Path State works it's a multiscale
blocking convolution tessellation
operation to group then SVD with
truncation to reduce to a defined State
space they only retain
32 of the variables from the
SVD at each
level
um there's more on this slide there's
but one thing that'll certainly be
interesting to discuss with the author
is at first glance this procedure may
appear to generate likelihood mappings
of increasing size because the
combinatorics of increasingly large
groups could explode at higher levels
however by training on a small number of
images One upper bounds the number of
states at each level
in other words one can effectively
encode a finite number of images without
any loss of information such that rgm
inversion corresponds to loss lless
compression so what's the deal with
training data how do we know about what
is going to be an optimal or effective
data size variability information
content or curriculum for the data set
how do we address that data selection
problem sometimes called active data
sampling
and then to the point about the lossless
compression one can effectively encode a
finite number of images without loss of
information so how how can or does this
do compression better than for example
gzip or llm that was a great moment in
computational history when people
realize that in certain ways these
models are doing information compression
and that even gzip or just file
compression utilities have attributes
that trained machine learning models
have because of information
Theory and how do we know and infer or
describe these tradeoffs related to the
training data set the structure of the
model all these different things as we
expand the scope of our modeling degrees
of freedom and H how has this problem
been solved similarly or approached
differently in other work on information
geometry in variational
autoencoders and and then just last
piece on working through this example so
again they they pre-processed the mnist
images the the images were downloaded
from the link
here they were converted to the format
that they
needed then they say an exampler image
is shown in figure three in the paper I
think that should be figure
four and then they're showing the
centroids of each of these groups so
this is just to get an intuition for
what this multiscale spin glass blocking
is doing with the success of clumping
and grouping into these multiple spatial
skills okay any
comments yeah I think I'm still very
confused as to how this ends up being
from the previous slide how you get
lossless compression if you're also
doing the singular value decomposition
and truncating some of those vectors um
yeah definitely want to follow up with
the office about when are we lossy and
when are we lossless uh and as you said
the question of training data and how
much what goes in your curriculum that's
going to be huge I think yeah good point
there's a truncation of variance so it's
if it's close to lossless that's also
known as lossy
compression um here is figure five
that's describing these concatenated
likelihood matrices this is a common
method in a lot of models where four
separate matrices can be included as
submatrices in a bigger Matrix that can
make it simpler to deal with in
programming it might make it amenable to
sparse Matrix methods or compression
methods it might make it just easier to
visualize but this is kind of a classic
trick going back to the SPM days um
okay if had imposed an additional
constraint or structural prior that
likelihood mappings are conserved
identically over groups so for example
if there was the prior that um let's
just talk about these four major
quadrants that's the third level of the
model if we had said all four of those
are the
same versus a situation like it was
which is it was left open upper left
quadrant of five could be different than
the bottom right right quadrant of
five if we had imposed that additional
constraint that the likelihood mappings
are conserved identically over groups
one would have the discrete homologue of
a convolutional neural network with
implicit weight
sharing so this is a Super Key point
because the people might have a lot more
familiarity with convolutional methods
from computer vision in the case where
the mappings are constrained to be the
same so it's a situation where we're
learning a single filter that optimally
sweeps across a whole image
this is the convolutional neural network
Case convolutional Case here in the
multiscale rgm The Learning space is
more complex it's more General so the
advantage is we could possibly describe
more conditional relationships like oh
the upper left quadrant of five looks
like this but the bottom right looks
like that what's the disadvantage you
know where is this lunch getting paid
for it massively expands the search and
training space as all always you can
have a more expressive model has more
options bigger search space less
expressive model smaller search space
and then figure six shows more about
what these scales look like and connects
it also to receptive fields in the
visual processing but just like the 4x4
spin block window or the 32 truncation
dimensions for SVD or the 10 levels of
this Factor that's a big question is
like what about 3x3 with 25 dimensions
of SVD and an eight factor or eight
levels for the factor so how how much
meta optimization do you do to determine
what these variables should
be one thing to pick up on that which
maybe maybe that maybe they they don't
do it in this paper but I'm sure they've
done in others is well if I need to
optimize something about my model why
don't I just create a bunch of them and
then check my free energy and just pick
the one with the lowest free energy so
parameter optimization through free
energy minimization happens everywhere
else in active inference I'm not sure
why we couldn't also do it here for some
of these um so You' set up your rgm but
you could have different parameters on
uh how many variables to how many
principal components to keep how many um
levels to do
Etc and so long as you can generate
observations and see which ones are the
most internally consistent with the
probabilities based on the training data
you could probably learn which like how
to do your
rgm yeah I think that's the dream is you
say here's the meta structure of the one
by one 2 x two 3x3 4x4 you know n
byn grouping and then we'll learn how
many n should we Group by on how many
levels per factor with how many variance
retention uh elements from the
SVD and then you say okay well should we
retain the same number of SVD variables
for every level or should we open up the
possibility that oh maybe the first
level we retain 10 but the second we
only retain three again that might be
more expressive If there really was 10
variance contribution in the first level
and three in the second but it's a
bigger search base so that's that's the
sort of meta question but that's
cognitive computer
so it's exciting times um figure seven
getting to the performance on The
Mist so figure five it says in the text
illustrates the results of active
learning but I think here they mean
figure
seven during exposure to the first
10,000 training images of the Mist data
set so in this example images were
assimilated if and only if they
increased the expected free energy the
rgm in the absence of Prior preferences
or constraints the this ensures minimum
information loss by underwriting
informative likelihood mappings at each
level so my question was does this
address the data sampling issue it seems
like they're selecting from a larger
data pool the informative examples which
improve the performance of EF so how
much to threshold or how to prioritize
that how do you deal with a path
dependence in training the order of the
curriculum of the points that are seen
or does it not matter but for real time
an online inference methods it often
really matters it's a complex landscape
so if you head out left or head out
right it's going to make a big
difference and isn't this substituting
another possibly quite
challenging inference and data selection
problem just so that a special smaller
rgm can be made so there's going to be
situations where it is worth that entry
cost cost to set up a smart active data
sampling method to train a powerful
rgm there might be another case where
the data sampling component is
challenging and it's not worth it and
there's another simpler way to do it
another way so of course in any specific
situation it's an empirical
question how these different methods
perform um and then just again what with
these images f Figure
um the thing to note here is
classification accuracy increases with a
marginal likelihood that each image
belongs to the class of numbers so here
they're showing that their accuracy is
very high where they're most confident
and their accuracy drops as their
confidence
drops and from a quick perplexity search
I also be curious to see what others
have to add classic shallow machine
machine learning algorithms can easily
achieve 90% 97% accuracy on mnist in
2015 convolutional neural networks
approach achieved an error rate of just
0.29% so 0 point I mean so so 99 plus
per. so especially at the way that
they're presenting it here without code
and things like that keep in mind that
it's more of a proof of concept in
analytic foundation not necessarily
being described as a computational
advance which would have a lot more
details on what was run rather than just
saying it was learned automatically
within a few seconds on a personal
computer that's kind of a casual way to
describe it I think it it's very
colorful and and inspirational though
more assessment would need to be looked
at how does how does the fit relate to
other methods and so this is a super
exciting open-source
direction to Poe empirical
reproducibility efforts to establish how
and when and where different code bases
do differently on different data
sets Okay yeah 100% just want to echo on
the making the code and things available
uh we really do need that uh it can't
just be in a mat lab script on carren's
computer it's got to be out there so
that we can use it and build on it and
understand what's going on um one thing
I think that's also worth uh
highlighting is this classification and
confidence question I'm not sure if the
convolution on your networks will also
give you that so if you if they classify
something maybe they just say oh I think
it's the num the digit zero and I'm like
95% confident I don't even know if you
get that necessarily like I think maybe
you get something that's a pseudo
confidence number on a scale of between
01 but it's not really confidence in the
same way that this is like this is like
you've got a probability distribution
and you can do do like a credible
interval on it if you want so I think
that's something to really really
highlight the
explainability is often in many cases
worth swapping a few percentage accuracy
points so that you know why your
algorithm has suggested something yeah
earlier work by a lot of those authors
have have highlighted that true element
of interpretability and uncertainty for
example in a llm today even if it does
say something like I'm not sure about X
that string I'm not sure about X was
actually achieved as a high confidence
outcome and so it doesn't actually
reflect an introspection of the
uncertainty intervals on X so fun topics
go to okay that was the first example
now we're going to go faster through the
next examples because they're structured
much the same way it's just each of
these following examples is going to
bring in a new dimension so the next
Dimension is going to be video
compression generalize the roral
renormalizing procedures the previous
section to include Dynamics for
recognizing and generating ordered
sequences of images so video is sequence
of
images also algorithm one has the fast
structure learning even just copying and
pasting this into perplexity and working
in curser from there does amazing things
so I'm super excited for what people
come up with in terms of using the
algorithms that are laid out and
implementing them in different languages
and so on so this section is going to
generalize the static univariate
grayscale example of amnest into an RGB
three color three Channel plus time time
color pixel voxal tupal
structure here's where we get to time
time wasn't present in the Mist example
but by partitioning each sequence into
non-overlapping pairs during the time
scale transformation at successive
levels one effectively halves the length
of a sequence when ascending from one
level to the next so we talked about
different ways to do nesting in time 60
minutes in an hour 24 hours in a day
here is going to be a strict frequency
doubling this means that higher levels
encode sequences of sequences of
sequences paging exhibit that can be
regarded as episodes of successive
events
so key idea State Path State Path State
path encodes transitions through time
and there's this inforced frequency
doubling so processes are encoded
relationally look into something like
successor representation learning or Q
learning to see some other
approaches um during inference the
separation of temporal scales manifests
as a particular kind of reactive message
passing
so it's possible to Define and use
message passing among
levels it could also be possible to
provide alternative operations orders or
like in RX and fur use graphs that have
no preset order of updating or other
rules for how updating occurs okay
here's where in figure 10 11 and 12 we
get to the example we used a short video
sequence of a dove flopping her wings
the original video was down sampled to
frames and they describe a little bit
more they use the same 4x4
blocking so this is key information on
the video
processing and it's really exciting to
think about what they do to these file
formats as analytic affordances I found
this actually more from the discourse
analysis area and rhetoric studies but
if think about the choices and the
degrees of freedom that are made in the
data processing and meta modeling those
are analytical affordances and it
relates to how we were talking about you
could do inference on those
variables and so here we see analogous
to the images that were output for the
mnist summaries and performance here we
similarly have prediction through time
of this Dove flapping the wings it's a
cyclic generated video and for
example the stimulus here is just if
like a spotlight is only on part of the
dove and then it can
reconstruct through space at the same
moment and Through Time how it will
continue to unfold given the patchy
observations that it gets so that's the
kind of Dove video
example I think there's one thing just
to yeah some background on why why does
that matter that you can just I'll do
the spotlight thing and recover the
original in a way um so this is a fairly
common way of understanding sort of like
unsupervised learning has your algorithm
actually understood the data um and so
that's a masking parts of the image and
asking it to infill it is a very common
way of testing that what you've got
actually understands what's going on and
it's not just going to hallucinate
anything random so
um yeah when I first came across that I
was oh this is a bit odd but then yeah
it's worth looking into just as
background of like well if you have an
unsupervised learning technique how do
you know it's actually doing a good
job yeah cool okay the next example in
the video section in the preceding
example the sequence of image
constitutes a closed path namely a
simple orbit so it's like a gif of the
dove flapping the wings it returns to
the same spot and then it continues
again this can be regarded as a
quantized representation of a periodic
attractor in the section paths orbits
and
attractors they use the same procedures
to compress and generate stochastic
chaos using images generated by a loren
system the aim of the example is to show
how active learning after structure
learning furnishes a generative model of
chaotic
orbits so the ren system and active
inference is discussed in the four-part
series on live stream 32 stochastic
chaos and marov blankets and here we see
an analogous process to the mnist
analogous to the dove we have an image
or sequences of images through time its
traces from this Loren's chaotic
attractor similarly there's this
grouping and reduction operation
happening through space and time and
then parameterization of those models
that's the structure learning followed
by parameterization result results in
the ability to have even when there's a
gap in the observations like in figure
15 on the right here we have a gap in
the observations but the predictive
posterior is able to continue it's an
empirical question how well it lines up
but this is just really fascinating
because it shows well even though the
generative process we can say has this
chaotic
instability that might make it anal
analytically intract ible from the
generative modeling perspective the rgm
enables a really nicely typed way that
can accommodate systems that have these
chaotic properties what what was
exciting to you about this
part uh yeah exactly that it's you know
chaos is fascinating uh and modeling it
famously very difficult um so yeah I
think I think this is actually I feel
like they should be sh about this more
in the paper in a way like maybe they
could have opened this I don't know um
but uh I would really like to see some
more like actually simpler examples of
chaotic systems being modeled in this
way and maybe that could be a separate
paper entirely um but even just you know
one-dimensional signals that that change
in time uh that are famously quite
chaotic that we don't do a very good job
of modeling would be really interesting
to see how getting that into an orbit uh
modeling procedure using this would be
and see how that goes we were very
excited to try that awesome yeah totally
agree um the next example continuing in
the image and video sequence is a bird
so a natural extension figure 16
illustrates the spatial blocking of a
more natural video a short sequence from
this website so that URL was no longer
active but either way it was just a
search URL so it'd be cool to see the
exact video maybe it could be uploaded
but either way this is a short video of
a bird in a natural setting and again
figure
17 staying with this
theme there's a Laten State prediction
ongoing even though the stimulus the
observation is withheld sometimes so in
a way that's like what happens when we
blink or have an icate we have this
ongoing posterior prediction of the
visual scene which is what's being
experienced or attended to with color
everywhere and equal Precision
everywhere and all this stuff including
continuity when we blink or have an
icade because it's basically what's
happening here there's just transiently
no stimulus but still the likeliest
thing that's happening is the lat and
state prediction so that last little
sequence took us from
handwriting static images grayscale into
three video settings which was a cylic
oscillatory synthetic video a synthetic
chaotic video and then a
natural video so you could imagine if
this was more structured natural video
it would be easier to learn with
probably any method if this was a more
complex scene with multiple different
things switching position I it would be
a harder video to
learn any more thoughts on the natural
extension yeah actually so if yeah so if
it's trained on this particular video
one thing I wasn't sure is what frames
does it predict sort of at the end so
we've talked about like oh if you like
Miss some frames in the middle and then
it can it can catch up and keep up but
if you just run this
indefinitely I'm not actually sure what
the bird would be predicted to do and
would it just eventually loot back
because it's sort of like you have that
chaotic path in the previous one it's
still an orbit it still returns to the
same attractor States whereas here I'm
not sure what the bird would do when
it's predicted to be doing stuff is
maybe just flies off the screen and we
don't see it anymore I don't know that's
it's it's kind of like a Sci-Fi
simulation to run it's like a Sci-Fi
like what if it's like the movie is an
hour and a half long and then you keep
watching it's like wait it's still going
what's
happening okay um the next case that
they study is sound so the video
examples in the prior three were just
transitions of it was an ordered
sequence of images whereas the video
more broadly understood like the live
stream that you're listening to now is
video as image plus audio so here they
just kind of leave the video behind and
say let's just look at the audio in this
setting pixels and there's an analogy
for the multimodal
llms where the tokenization methods that
work for natural language in the discret
setting also work for tokenization of
image and audio like GPT 40 so in this
setting pixels I.E picture elements are
replaced by voxal volume elements over
frequency and
time these constitute time frequency
representation of Time series or a
continuous wavelet transform
cwt renormalizing models for sound are
simpler than for video content because
there's only one metric Dimension
frequency that accompanies time using a
spin block transformation to core scin
over frequency reflects the factor
assumption that neighboring frequencies
fluctuate in a correlated fashion so
kind of similar data availability
setting URL provided but unclear what
the songs were and then we see the
similar visual representations
culminating in for example 20 where
predictions Laten State predictions are
able to continue even though part of the
stimulus has been
redacted so it's kind of like a a video
chat or a phone call and then someone
drops out for a few seconds but you're
able to still have your
unrolling
expectations about what did happen even
though you might be missing some
observations so any comments on this
first first sound
part uh no let's carry on all right good
from sounds to music one might ask if
rgms could be applied to language
perhaps in the spirit of hierarchical
derish lay process models we will not
address this here but provide an
application to music to gener to
illustrate the generalized synchrony
that accompanies communicative Exchange
fris in and fith 2015 the classic song
bird diad so keep in mind that the birds
that are in this diotic Songbird setting
which is also reflected in the 2022
textbook are literally singing from the
same sheet music they have the same
single fixed song so it's not modeling
the flow of language as
conversation at the level of new lexemic
information provided like go to the
store and get me milk or meta lexemic
like prootic or stylist elements of
language it's a very restricted sense of
language but it's part of the tech tree
of building towards models that capture
more sophisticated elements of language
but here is more structured than this
sound example it it'd be interesting to
hear some of these songs in their um
original versions and in their generated
versions and like how well does this do
from a performance and file size
perspective how well does that do to MP3
which is another example of data
compression and that's exactly like the
gzip and llm comparison earlier if at
the heart of a variational auto encoder
or an rgm or something else is using a
structurally determined model as
parameterized to have a smaller
representation of a larger
space how do these physics inspired
first principles of intelligence models
or classical machine learning and
compression related models
do are we getting what fraction of
compression how good is the performance
all these you know can you tune the bit
rate all those kinds of
questions okay on to the last
section from pixels to planning
so in the final section we turn to the
deployment of rgms for planning as
inference and implicitly their use as
synthetic agents and decision makers
under uncertainty so we're getting to
the generalized active agents which is
to say the capacity for control and
navigation in arbitrary
spaces and so here we also see uh
comparison or J toos of active inference
and reward learning and ran way give a
great guest stream recently on
similarities and differences there um
and they make some more comments about
how the
rgm has relationships with
generalized multi-level learning so now
we're kind of briefly dropping any
specific case like a data set of images
or video and just thinking more
generally about how this rgm could be
used for multiscale active
agents any
comments uh no no SC up um
procedurally this looks very much like
conventional reinforcement learning
however it is simpler and more efficient
because it learns a compressed
representation of and only of paths that
link rewarded States so that might have
some connections with the inductive
Behavior paper that they also wrote
another way of looking at this is smart
data
selection that relates to my earlier
question of well if you knew which data
to select and in what order for free
then maybe
the model can be trained
effectively but if it's a hard problem
to determine which data to sample or
what order to do it in then it's just
substituting one type of problem for
another which might be effective in a
situation but that's not a general
approach effectively this leads to the
automatic selection of model structures
that can only recognize and predict
rewarding episodes thereby
eluding subsequent parameter
learning this rests upon the fact that
one does not need to learn how to
maximize reward if one has a generative
model that can only predict paths that
lead to
reward I was a bit uncertain about this
because
different paths may probabilistically
lead to different reward and then I
thought well wait a minute that's just
pragmatic value what about the automatic
selection of model structures that can
only recognize and predict epistemic
information isn't the expected free
energy
going to be able to select data active
data sampling live stream 57 smart data
selection according to epistemic plus
pragmatic
value and thereby specify the next
action again reinforcement learning
selects the next action based upon
highest expected value or reward but
expected free energy has epistemic plus
pragmatic
value in what follows we will illustrate
this approach in sequential policy
optimization and unack some of its
cories games and attractors so here they
use Simple Atari like games to show how
a model of expert play self assembles
given a sequence of outcomes under
random
actions the first simple game in
question is a game of
pong they describe how they cor scin the
blocks and then they selected frames
that started from a successful outcome
so they trained on successful examples
in short we use rewards for and only for
data selection so that's kind of an
interesting
possibility that there's a pragmatic
filter on training data followed by then
an epistemic openness to whatever it is
that that data
has um and renormalization happens
through space and time
like the video examples and through the
action policy that's the section that
we're in here where we're saying in the
general case we're also able to do rgm
on nested policy but here there was just
one time scale of
policy um figure 25 26 and 27 go over
some of those representations so any
thoughts on
this uh yeah I think it's the training
part is really interesting and what that
I think maybe possibly as well we're
getting a bit closer as to why they use
that c the C letter for paths if it's
only
ever Cod encoding paths that are
rewarding then we sort of Go full circle
back to the definition in the power
textbook of C as like rewards uh it's
just rewarded paths rather than rewards
of OB observation
um but I think they come on to this
later on in the paper this feels like a
very Britt way of training a model if it
only ever encounters positive States or
like things that it likes or things that
we want it to like what happens if you
drop it in a situation that it hasn't
seen before where there's a negative
State and it has no way to recover back
to a positive one so if you think of a
in like for training on a game if you
start in a losing State how do you how
do you bring it back how how do you
recover um so I think that that's
something that we will come on to later
but it's a really interesting thing to
bear in mind of well what are you
training on are you only training on
success how do you deal with failure
yeah great point that also makes me
wonder about the transfer applicability
so we train it on that bird video but
then what if it's the same bird but it's
just a little bit darker light or it's a
different angle what are the transfer
limits or what is really training
on and then especially if there's a sort
of data filtering or selection to past
data that is one of the critiques of
large data set related training so maybe
this uses a subset of it like a filtered
subset since there's already a database
of successful and unsuccessful
plays just selecting the successful ones
and then at the same time there's this
interesting biological tie-in which is
like the organism's training data
through life in a way is all successful
with respect to
survival so by having the training data
only reflect a certain kind of
success perhaps with a lot of
variability still it it's an interesting
question what it learns and how
transferable that could
be and then
this is the last of the worked examples
figure 28 shows the same simulation
using a slightly more complicated game
based upon breakout so what's happening
in these game play settings is game play
is like a video plus controllable State
transitions so it'd be like if there was
a dove flapping its wings and then also
there was another parameter which was
lights on or lights off
and then there's one latent state which
is where is the Dove's Wings really and
then how does the Dove's wing state get
emitted to observations when the light
is on or off and then that would be like
a simple example where the dove does not
respond to the light and then a more
complex example would be oh it flaps
differently in the light and the dark
and so that's where you start getting
into these factorized models and paths
on States on paths and States uh so here
they studi this game breakout where
there's in a way Niche modification
happening it doesn't show any of the
cells on the top getting broken but that
would be interesting how does it
represent down into the really fine
scale what numbers represent the
presence or absence of a block and how
does that really get
encoded so any any last comments before
we go to the conclusion
uh I actually found this example the
most difficult to follow in the
paper um I think it
it's it's still not entirely clear to me
how this RG operator handles the action
inside this as well um and how you cor
scin the effects of action that might
happen at a particular time step that
then gets sort of diluted out as it were
so uh that's just something I think from
for this for the game setion that I'd
quite like to ask the authors about is
uh to go into a bit more detail on the
RG operators when action is happening
but that action can only happen on a
particular time
like uh what's the word uh sort of
period as it
were yeah also I wasn't sure if these
were meant to be empty or if something
but then I wondered well is there a
natural interpretation of levels 1 2 and
three three and do these scale
separations capture some natural
components of the game or is there a
possibility that by using like a 4x4 any
n byn or using a strict doubling of time
that there's kind of an aliasing where
real natural scales of
analysis get sort of chopped up
strangely with different time scale
separations and so then it depends a lot
on what spatial and temporal scales are
divided on and then there would be some
training data for some partitionings
that would work really
well like if you had a ton of good
information on the structure of a
problem then maybe one measurement would
be all you needed like if you knew the
whole class schedule of the university
and how all the class beginnings and
endings were related and then someone
said there's a lecture in that Hall on
Tuesday and then you could have a ton of
information about how that was
correlated with everything else but then
if you were studying it on a meter by
meter subdivision on a time scale that
wasn't related to the time scale that
classes were happening you might need a
ton of data and still be shocked with
the next time
step so that's just the structure
learning Challenge and I think that is
is the Hope in the question how can
automated semi-automated and ultimately
unified methods for structure learning
be
applied okay
conclusion the paper has showcased
several applications of a generative
model for discrete State space
approaches based on the renormalization
group the appeal to the apparatus of the
normalization group is relatively
straightforward in the set
this is because active inference is an
application of the free energy principle
which is itself a variational principle
of least action whose functional form is
conserved over scales or hierarchical
levels having said this the Restriction
to spin block Transformations and pixel
spaces could also be regarded as a
limitation classic
answer in principle any outcome space
could be a candidate for course
graining how do we know understand and
balance where and when these spin blocks
would work or not we've discussed or and
and in other
conversations the applicability the
viability of doing sweeps and structure
learning and act on AC on ACM on RL on
AC on RL and how how many layers back
before your data science team is just
like I think this is fine rgm with
quantise paths may or may not be useful
in certain application domains the
applications above illustrate the
Simplicity and efficiency with which the
structure of the models can be learned
so that's the key claim that's the key
Point further limitations the approach
described above rest on the efficiency
of the accompanying methods the
efficiency is both a gift and a burden
again
great clearly in terms of sample
efficiency and compression the schemes
described above are designed to
outperform Conventional learning scheme
okay but designed to
outperform is something that anyone can
say so did they outperform when other
learning schemes weren't presented in
the
paper this follows because model
construction procedure is
constructive as approach to the
reductive approach of basy model
reduction and related
procedures enabling the self- Assembly
of a minimally expressive model to
recognize generate and predict the
content at hand so that's this bottom up
construction through tessellation that
we've discussed this should be
contrasted with the reductive but but
not to be confused necessarily with
reductionism or reductionist account but
reductive in terms of starting with a
large overly expressive model that's
reduced or pruned minimizing complexity
to recover predictive validity and
generalization so one way to think about
that is like in the Vie the latent space
is a bow tie it's smaller in the middle
whereas as for an image processing
neural network you might take in 64
pixels output 64 pixels but then the
thickness in the middle is
huge so these are the approaches saying
well you can kind of have this
constructivist approach to building a
smaller Laten space that's projected
down to and then unpacked from that's
the vae rgm type
style another approach is to start with
a massive surfit of par parameters you
know 70 billion 405 billion and then use
that as a function
approximator to fit an approximation to
some other
function but more generally H how could
efficiency be a
burden
um they make some more points about
learning and skills and this gets to our
question about the successful uh Tri for
training so these such models are
necessarily
brittle in the sense they will not
recognize or respond to events they have
not previously
encountered that almost seems like too
far to say I mean the Mist model will be
able to respond to a digit it has never
encountered it won't be able to respond
to a temperature reading because it just
doesn't even have that capacity but it's
like out of sample learning or out of
structure learning a useful heris here
is learning to ride a
bike in this kind of procedural learning
we learn from a starting position and
accumulate successive cycles of pedaling
until we avoid falling completely but we
do fall and we learn from when we fall
in other words we retain only
experiences characteristic of successful
bike riding until we can ride fluently
however we have not we would not have
been we would not be able to ride a bike
starting from any arbitrary State EG
falling over
we would have to return to a known
starting position to recover our
flow flow is meant in manifold which
itself's upon pun senses here the
fluency associated with being in the
flow control flow dynamical flow and of
course RG
flow so what is really being claimed
about what are the situations where
successful examples are
enough where negative examples are and
aren't learned from or recovered to
and then how well did these methods work
within and out of
sample after all that is what the whole
question is in training a model is how
well do you do on the training and the
test for different kinds of out of
sample being from really similar but not
in the exact training data itself all
the way on through totally different
kinds of
work so
we don't know the next steps or
implications we have a lot of questions
and hopefully do
too what are you looking forward to or
just what what what what are your
thoughts having now gone through all of
this
and um yeah I'd love to see some code
I'd love to see some implementations
that we can hack around with
ourselves um
and yeah I think it's a really
because a lot of what's come in the past
for active inference has been it's felt
very like I need to write my generative
model down on paper I need to really sit
down and think undistracted and think
how do I model this problem what are the
causes what are the observations how do
they how might they relate and then I
create a function which will generate
these observations and then you can plug
into active inference and go all the way
but the often the hardest part is
writing writing down those a b CD
matrices right it's actually really
difficult for lots of people you know
you can be a train physicist and it's
still really hard to think how do I
model this problem in the real world in
terms of mathematical matrices that's
really hard so in theory if your RG
operators are good enough and you just
you can just Chuck some data Maybe it
has to all be positive data all the
happy past stuff but that's already
quite powerful I think um and moves I
think of inference closer to more
traditional machine learning in terms of
accessibility and ease of use so that
data science teams could just use this
in production I think we this is this
paper does represent quite a significant
step forward for that um and I think you
know with all the work that you've done
on this channel of just making a
inference more accessible and easier to
play around with easier to try in new
scenarios that's that's such a good
thing so very excited for the future
live stream sessions on this paper
awesome yeah great point
that how much of the modeling
specification today and tomorrow will be
manual semi-automated automated like
would you just put in the EEG data and
just say go for it or how would you
embody side information about the EEG
problem and then how would it do on
train and test and how would it transfer
all these different questions
so it's great do you have any last
comments uh yeah I just think the
explainability thing is going to be the
key here so as soon as you go to
unsupervised sort of structure learning
what did those levels mean and what do
those factors mean that it's learned
from the data itself if I if we go the
old fashioned route if I come up with a
generative model and I say this is how
I'm modeling the system I can explicitly
say this level this latent variable is
for whether it's raining or not and this
observation corresponds to water
observed on the grass outside but
because I'm coming up that model I can
use words to communicate that to you and
you have that full explainability of
this model with this approach we are
going to lose some of that and it'll be
really interesting to see how whether we
can recover the explainability of well
what does this factor mean when I did a
principal components transformation and
dished half the components
what does that actually mean you could
sort of look at it on the MST example
and go oh yeah it's a digit right but we
still have to look at that so getting
that in an semi-automated way be very
exciting as well yeah that makes me
think about what natural joints of the
world handles for the world
will a possibly automated method fail to
find and then conversely what new
natural scales might it come up with for
example just doing PCA analysis on
natural language it's like okay
principal component one is whether it's
happy or sad or whether it's written in
this language or that language but then
you get the principal component seven
and it's like huh does that igen term
mean
something with it a little bit more of
this and a little bit less of that does
that what does that really mean and then
the further you go wow usually the less
reliable those variance components are
across different data
sets so then that comes back to H how do
we
interpret and set up systems that have
few or many you know when shorter lists
are more
interpretable but then when you Clump
under fewer things they have more
grouping of dis similar things so it's
like lumpers and Splitters the neats and
the
scruffies those those are all coming to
play right on that field so thank you
very much Aron and also to Blue and to
Courtney for the contributions to
thezero so looking forward to the next
two weeks
peace thanks very
much e